Now to an ABC News investigation. Half
of all the new demand for electricity
over the next 5 years in the US is
expected to come from data centers. They
are the backbone of AI technology. In
partnership with our stations across the
country, our Elizabeth Schelsey shows us
how they're dividing communities,
bringing the promise of new jobs, but
fears of higher utility bills.
>> This was the sound at Laura Evans home
in suburban Chicago last spring when
backup generators kicked in at the data
center. 1,000 ft from her backyard.
>> And it never goes away.
>> Never goes away.
>> Laura tells us the data center emits a
low hum 24/7. [music] And it's not just
the noise taking a toll. She says in the
last year, her average electricity bill
has spiked 23%. And
>> how do you budget when it's changing
that much in one year?
>> You can't.
>> And the electric company warned prices
could rise even more. They need more
power at the data centers.
>> Saying one reason why is increased
electricity use from data centers and
artificial intelligence.
>> The energy demand from these facilities
affects our ability to meet clean energy
goals, have a livable planet, and also
just pay our bills.
>> ABC News and our owned and affiliated
stations spoke with communities across
the country grappling with the rapid
buildup of data centers to support the
AI boom. An analysis from our data team
found there are more than 3,000 data
centers in the US. About 1,200 more are
now under construction or soon to be
built.
>> If you're watching a show or if you're
using AI, ultimately a lot of the
computation happening there, or at least
the storage for that thing is in a data
center somewhere.
>> And our analysis finds a majority of the
country's large data centers are or will
be in cities, towns, or developed
suburbs.
>> You need a really well-developed, very
consistent grid. They need to be
extremely reliable in the energy that
they use because if a data center
suddenly goes out, if it completely
loses power, all the tens of thousands
of people who are interacting with it
are suddenly going to be very mad.
>> When these data centers go offline, your
apps can go down almost right away.
>> Exactly.
>> So, this is pretty much as close as
we're going to get to where this data
center is popping up. Just a massive
construction site. Hard to comprehend
the scale of this. 2-hour drive north of
Laura's home, we visited the site of
what will be one of the biggest data
centers in the US in the small town of
Port Washington, Wisconsin.
A$ 15 billion project backed by OpenAI
and Oracle that's part of the White
House's Stargate initiative announced on
President Trump's second day in office.
The campus sits on a plot of farmland
bigger than 500 football fields and will
eventually use about the same amount of
electricity needed to keep the lights on
in all the homes in Philadelphia.
>> They'd be putting power lines that are
taller than apparently the uh Statue of
Liberty.
>> Tom Utek has lived on this land for 40
years. He's an artist who draws
inspiration from its natural beauty.
Last year, he got a letter from his
utility company saying it plans to build
a massive power line for the data center
right across his property.
>> I had no choice. Uh and basically
they're saying that if you don't agree,
we will take it by eminent domain.
>> They'll just take over your land.
>> Yeah. And we'll fight it to the end.
>> He showed us where the power line would
go, wiping out dozens of trees he
planted. There's no way this environment
around this neighborhood could ever be
the same if it's uh cut in half again by
these giant things.
>> We expect attendees will act in a civil
manner at all times.
>> At a town hall this month, we saw how
the data center is dividing the
community.
>> We need clarity and we need it now
because we are not going to pay double
the amount of our utility bills. Do you
understand that? These are good paying
union jobs that are part of a once- in a
generation investment in Port
Washington.
>> Mayor Ted Nitsky defends the project.
>> These are huge companies that are kind
of the face of AI right now. Open AAI,
Oracle. Are you convinced that they will
be willing to invest in this community?
>> They've been awesome. I mean, they have
been they have met every expectation
we've given them.
>> He says the data center will create
4,000 temporary construction jobs and
bring in much needed tax revenue. My
greatest fear was that I would wake up
one day and our downtown would be a
ghost town again. And as a dad who
raised my kids here and was born and
raised here, I wanted this to be a
better place.
>> But some residents still aren't buying
it.
>> This is an abuse of power.
>> The mayor even facing an attempt to
recall him from office that ultimately
failed.
>> This video shows one opponent who
chanted recall at a city meeting last
December. She's handcuffed and
physically removed from the meeting by
police.
>> It was uh incredibly shocking. Um I
never imagined anything like that ever
happening.
>> There was a pretty heated moment a
couple months ago at one of the council
meetings.
>> What are you doing?
>> How do you react to the backlash from
the video?
>> How do I react to it? I can play you the
voicemails of the threats I received
from all over the country to my family
safety. I can play you the voicemails of
the threats to our police department
from all over the country.
>> In statements to ABC News, the tech
companies behind the Wisconsin project
pointed to economic benefits for the
region.
Open AAI said, "In Wisconsin and across
all our US Stargate sites, we are
committed to paying our own way on
energy so that our operations do not
increase local electricity prices."
Oracle added it will invest in wind,
solar, and batteries, which means more
reliable, affordable energy will be
available to local families and
businesses. And Tom Utek's utility
company tells us the route it has chosen
for the power line offers a lower cost
to rateayers and maximizes the use of
existing corridors.
>> Why should people who don't live in this
area, might not ever come to this part
of Wisconsin, [music]
care about what's happening?
They should care because uh it's their
backyard. Next,
>> back in Laura Evans backyard in Aurora,
Illinois, local officials made the
decision to put a 180day pause on
building new data centers. We basically
put a pause to make sure that if these
data centers want to come in, that they
can be good neighbors going forward and
try to really address some of the
concerns that our citizens have. The
city's pause on new data centers, which
ends next month, was a way to buy time
for local officials like Allison
Lindberg to put new regulations in
place. Is the conversation around how to
regulate data centers happening fast
enough as how much they're popping up
right now?
>> I I definitely think that the
regulations need to be happening faster.
The fact that we as this smallalish city
are the ones that are leading in this is
is frankly pretty surprising considering
the magnitude of um the impact of these
data centers. In a statement to ABC
News, the data center just behind
Laura's home apologized to neighbors and
said it is committed to supporting
policies that accelerate new power
supply and grid technologies to improve
reliability and moderate costs over
time. And it installed temporary noise
barriers while permanent engineered
solutions were being designed and
fabricated.
>> Some proponents of this technology say
this is the future. What do you say to
that?
>> Build it somewhere else and just make
sure it's done right because this isn't
right.